Guide to the George Altomare United Federation of Teachers Audio Collection OH.087
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Altomare United Federation of Teachers Audio Collection
circa 1960-1989
1975-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Altomare, George.
OH.087
2 Linear Feet in 2 media boxes.
The United Federation of Teachers, a New York-based teachers union, was founded in 1960 with a merger of the Teachers Guild and the High School Teachers Association. George Altomare was a founding member of the UFT. The collection contains thirty-eight cassettes and two open reels recorded by Altomare. The recordings are comprised of a mixture of symposiums, debates, meetings, and oral history interviews. Topics include labor heritage, Italian and Irish involvement in the profession, pensions, and teacher experiences.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by George Altomare in 1989. The accession number associated with this gift. 1989.020.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note
The United Federation of Teachers, a New York-based teachers union, was founded in 1960 with a merger of the Teachers Guild and the High School Teachers Association. George Altomare was a founding member and leader in the UFT.
Custodial History
The collection was donated by George Altomare in 1989. Altomare had created these recordings at United Federation Teacher events, but they were not owned by the UFT or a part of its records.
Related Archival Materials
United Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection (OH 009)
United Federation of Teachers Records (WAG 022)
United Federation of Teachers: Italian-American Studies Committee Records. (WAG 56)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains thirty-eight cassettes and two open reels recorded by United Federation of Teachers member George Altomare. The recordings are comprised of a mixture of symposiums, debates, meetings, and oral history interviews. Events of the Italian-American Studies and Irish-American Studies committees are also represented. Two reels address teacher pension issues in the 1960s. There are also five oral history interviews with UFT members. The collection documents union activities, the union's sense of heritage, the relationship between ethnic communities and the UFT, and teacher experiences.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York; United Federation of Teachers
- Ellis Ostrove on Pensions, New York State Teachers' Retirement System, circa 1960 (Box 1)
- Dave Wittes Addresses School Meeting on Pensions, circa 1965 (Box 1)
- Clara Maymand Interview (Rich, Rick, Elise, Gluck), Dec 18, 1975 (Box 2)
- Charlie Cogen (Richy and Ricky), Dec 23, 1975 (Box 2)
- Alice Marsh Interview, Jan 9, 1976 (Box 2)
- Reuben Mitchell Interview, Jan 26, 1977 (Box 2)
- Michael Mann at UFT, "The Irish Character", Mar 16, 1978 (Box 2)
- Labor Heritage Week Teachers Symposium: Mollisani, etc., 1979 (Box 2)
- Italian American Symposium, 1979 (Box 2)
- Teachers Union Day - Seminar and Luncheon, Nov 9, 1980 (Box 2)
- Teachers Union Day - Luncheon (continued), Reuben Mitchell speech, Nov 7, 1980 (Box 2)
- Teachers Union Day - Luncheon, Kolodny's acceptance of Charles Cogan Award, Nov 8, 1981 (Box 2)
- Labor Heritage: Teachers Symposium (ATSS and UFT), Nov 7, 1981 (Box 2)
- HS Committee - George Altomare, Special Ed, Nathan Quinones, Jan 12, 1982 (Box 2)
- ELAC - Charlotte Frank, Board of Education on IOS, Jan 14, 1982 (Box 2)
- Jefferson High School - Redistricting Public Meeting (UFT), Feb 18, 1982 (Box 2)
- Jewish Heritage, Apr 29, 1982 (Box 2)
- Debates between Altomare and Schulman at Madison High School and Eastern District High School, Mar 1983 (Box 2)
- UFT Italian American Studies Committee Symposium, May 5, 1983 (Box 2)
- Excellence and Equity Conference, Feb 10, 1984 (Box 2, Box 1, Folder 1)
- Italian Heritage Symposium, May 8, 1984 (Box 2)
- UFT Labor Heritage, Nov 27, 1984 (Box 2)
  Scope and Content Note
  Includes Doris Turner, "On the Role of Labor Unions Today" and Paul Cole, "Teaching About Labor Unions."
- Labor Heritage: Professor Yellowitz on 50th Anniversary of Wagner Act, Nov 27, 1984 (Box 2)
- Labor Heritage, Nov 30, 1984 (Box 2)
- HS Committee - HS DR Election, Dec 11, 1984 (Box 2)
- A conversation between Arthur Schneider and Robert Feigin, Jan 12, 1985 (Box 2)
- Symposium: Italian American Studies Committee of the UFT and Jewish Labor Committee Education Chapter, May 8, 1985 (Box 2)
- HS Committee Meeting, part 1, Jun 4, 1985 (Box 2)
- HS Committee Meeting, part 2, Jun 4, 1985 (Box 2)
- Italian American Symposium, Oct 24, 1985 (Box 2)
- UFT Irish American Heritage, Mar 9, 1988 (Box 2, Box 1, Folder 1)
  Program recorded to three cassettes. Content includes George Altomare on Bill McGinn, Dr. Maureen Murphy on Irish Patriots in America, and Eileen Condon leading Irish Ballads. There is also a paper program of the proceedings.
- Scholarship Winner - Rolando Acosta, undated (Box 2)
- Nick Spilotro, undated (Box 2)
- The Irish Character, undated (Box 2)